<sect2>
<title>Configuring <application>tripwire</application></title>

<sect3><title>Config files</title>
<para><filename>/etc/tripwire</filename></para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Configuration Information</title>

<para><application>Tripwire</application> uses a policy file to determine which 
files integrity are checked. The default policy file (<filename>twpol.txt
</filename> found in <filename>/etc/tripwire/</filename>) is for a default 
installation of Redhat 7.0 and is woefully outdated.</para>

<para>Policy files are also a custom thing and should be tailored to each 
individual distribution and/or installation. Some custom policy files can be 
found below: </para>
<screen><ulink  url="http://home.iprimus.com.au/glombowski/blfs/twpol-all.txt"/>
Checks integrity of all files
<ulink url="http://home.iprimus.com.au/glombowski/blfs/twpol-lfs.txt"/>
Custom policy file for Base LFS 3.0 system
<ulink url="http://home.iprimus.com.au/glombowski/blfs/twpol-suse7.2.txt"/>
Custom policy file for SuSE 7.2 system</screen>

<para>Download the custom policy file you'd like to try, copy it into <filename>
/etc/tripwire/</filename>, and use it instead of <filename>twpol.txt
</filename>. It is, however, recommended that you make your own policy file. 
Get ideas from the examples above and read <filename>
/usr/share/doc/tripwire/policyguide.txt</filename>. <filename>twpol.txt
</filename> is a good policy file for beginners as it will note any changes to 
the filesystem and can even be used as an annoying way of keeping track of 
changes for uninstallation of software.</para>

<para>After your policy file has been transferred to <filename>/etc/tripwire/
</filename> you may begin the configuration steps:</para>

<screen><userinput><command>twadmin -m P /etc/tripwire/twpol.txt &amp;&amp;
tripwire -m i</command></userinput></screen>

<para>During configuration tripwire will create 2 keys: a site key and
 a local key which will be stored in <filename class="directory">/etc/tripwire/
</filename>.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3><title>Usage Information</title>
<para>To use tripwire after this and run a report, use the following command:

<screen><userinput><command>tripwire -m c &gt; /etc/tripwire/report.txt
</command></userinput></screen></para>

<para>View the output to check the integrity of your files. An automatic
integrity report can be produced by using a cron facility to schedule
the runs. </para>

<para>Please note that after you run an integrity check, you must check
the report or email and then modify the tripwire database of the files
on your system so that tripwire will not continually notify you that
files you intentionally changed are a security violation. To do this you
must first <command>ls /var/lib/tripwire/report/</command> and note
the name of the newest file which starts with <filename>linux-</filename> and 
ends in <filename>.twr</filename>. This encrypted file was created during the 
last report creation and is needed to update the tripwire database of your 
system. Then, type in the following command making the appropriate 
substitutions for '?':
<screen><userinput><command>tripwire -m u -r /var/lib/tripwire/report/linux-???????-??????.twr </command></userinput></screen></para>

<para>You will be placed into vim with a copy of the report in front of you. If 
all the changes were good, then just type <command>:x</command> and after 
entering your local key, the database will be updated. If there are files which 
you still want to be warned about, please remove the x before the filename in 
the report and type <command>:x</command>. </para>

</sect3>

<sect3><title>Changing the Policy File</title>

<para>If you are unhappy with your policy file and would like to modify it or 
use a new one, modify the policy file and then execute the following commands:
<screen><userinput><command>twadmin -m P /etc/tripwire/twpol.txt &amp;&amp;
tripwire -m i</command></userinput></screen></para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

