<sect2>
<title>Contents</title>

<para>The transcode package contains <userinput>transcode</userinput>,
<userinput>tccat</userinput>, <userinput>tcdecode</userinput>,
<userinput>tcdemux</userinput>, <userinput>tcextract</userinput>,
<userinput>tcframe</userinput>, <userinput>tcprobe</userinput>,
<userinput>tcscan</userinput>, <userinput>avicodec</userinput>,
<userinput>avidump</userinput>, <userinput>avimerge</userinput>,
<userinput>avisplit</userinput>, <userinput>avisync</userinput> and
a merry lot of input/filter/output modules.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2><title>Description</title>

<sect3><title>transcode</title>
<para>transcode is the encoder's user interface that handles the plugins
and other programs, being the glue between the modules.
There are several well documented usage examples on either the homepage
or the documentation included in the package.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tccat</title>
<para>tccat concatenates input files using the input plugins of 
transcode.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcdecode</title>
<para>tcdecode is used to decode input files to raw video and pcm audio
stream.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcdemux</title>
<para>tcdemux demultiplexes audio/video input that contains multiple
streams, e.g. VOB-files.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcextract</title>
<para>tcextract grabs single streams from a file containing multiple
streams.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcframe</title>
<para>tcframe processes single video frames for different color encodings
(RGB &gt;-&lt; YUV or similar).</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcprobe</title>
<para>tcprobe prints informations about the input file format.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>tcscan</title>
<para>tcscan performs several measurements on the given input 
data.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>avicodec</title>
<para>avicodec indicates or changes FOURCC codec flag in an .avi 
file.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>avidump</title>
<para>avidump dumps audio or video stream of an given avifile to
stdout (for avi conversion or extraction of audio streams).</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>avimerge</title>
<para>avimerge merges avi files of the same format. Do not try to merge
avi files of different formats, it will most likely result in errors (and
format means same bitrates, too!).</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>avisplit</title>
<para>avisplit splits avi files into multiple files.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>avisync</title>
<para>avisync can shift audio in avi files for better synchronizing of
audio and video data signal.</para></sect3>

<sect3><title>input/filter/output modules</title>
<para>Depending on the external libraries that are used, there are a great
number of plugins to convert audio and video input to raw format, process
raw video and audio and convert raw audio and video to other formats to be
written into a filetype of choice. Read the documentation.</para></sect3>

</sect2>

