<sect1 id="preface-organization">
<?dbhtml filename="organization.html" dir="preface"?>
<title>Organization</title>

<para>This book is divided into the following parts.</para>

<sect2><title>Part I - Introduction</title>
<para>This part contains information which is essential to
the rest of the book.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part II - Post LFS Configuration and Extra Software</title>
<para>Here we introduce basic configuration and security issues.  We also
discuss a range of editors, filesystems and shells which aren't covered in
the main LFS book.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part III - General Libraries and Utilities</title>
<para>In this section we cover libraries which are often needed by the rest
of the book as well as system utilities.  Information on Programming
(including recompiling gcc to support its full range of languages) concludes
this part.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part IV - Connecting to a Network</title>
<para>Here we cover how to connect to a network when you aren't using 
the simple static IP setup given in the main LFS book.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part V - Basic Networking</title>
<para>Networking libraries and command line networking tools make up the
bulk of this part.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part VI - Server Networking</title>
<para>Here we deal with setting up mail and other servers (such as SSH,
CVS, etc.).</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part VII - Content Serving</title>
<para>In this part we deal with databases and web server software (including
php).</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part VIII - X + Window Managers</title>
<para>This part explains how to set up a basic XFree86 installation along
with some generic X libraries and Window managers.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part IX - KDE</title>
<para>For those who want to use the K Desktop Environment or some parts of
it, this part covers it.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part X - Gnome</title>
<para>Gnome is the main alternative to KDE in the Desktop Environment arena
and we cover both gnome-1.4 and gnome-2.2 here.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part XI - X Software</title>
<para>Office programs and graphical web browsers are important to most
people.  They, along with some generic X software can be found in this part
of the book.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part XII - Multimedia</title>
<para>Here we cover setting multimedia libraries and drivers along with some
audio, video and CD-writing programs.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Part XIII - Printing, Scanning and Typesetting</title>
<para>The PST part of the book covers things from ghostscript, cups and DocBook 
to installing TeX.</para></sect2>

<sect2><title>Appendices</title>
<para>The Appendices cover information which doesn't belong in the main
book; they are mainly there as a reference.</para></sect2>

</sect1>
