<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="bulletin" xreflabel="Bulletin">
  <?dbhtml filename="bulletin.html"?>


  <title>Bulletin</title>

  <para>Current release: &version; &ndash; &releasedate;</para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Bulletin Entries:</title>

    <!-- News template
    <sect3>
      <title>~ Title</title>
      <para>MMMM DD{nd,st,th}, YYYY</para>

      <para>News.</para>
      <para>- Name</para>
    </sect3>
    -->
    
    <sect3>
      <title>~ Planned Site and Repo Switch</title>
      <para>September 6th, 2024</para>

      <para>
        Sometime down the road, this book will no longer be updated on this
        site (<ulink url="https://zeckmathederg.github.io/glfs"/>) and its
        current repo (<ulink url="https://github.com/Zeckmathederg/glfs"/>).
      </para>

      <para>
        Development will switch over to the repo
        <ulink url="https://github.com/glfs-book/glfs"/> after all the
        <ulink url="https://github.com/Zeckmathederg/glfs/issues">current
	issues</ulink> in the current repo are completed, so it may take a
        while before this switch will happen. Please make new issues on the
        <ulink url="https://github.com/glfs-book/glfs">new repo</ulink> and
        they will be dealt with afterwards.
      </para>

      <para>
        As for the site, it will be decided when the time is ready and this
        book will display where the updated one is.
      </para>

      <para>
        This is all done to make things more professional and to separate the
        project from my account. I also have plans that will make things more
        interesting.
      </para>

      <para>- Zeckma</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>~ Hiatus Over</title>
      <para>June 16th, 2024</para>

      <para>I'm back and working on this book again. Simple
      announcement but this will do.</para>
      <para>- Zeckma</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>~ Hiatus</title>
      <para>June 14th, 2024</para>

      <para>
        I will be going on an indefinite hiatus. Disappointed and
        bummed out. The subsection of <xref linkend="sdchapter"/>
        named "Drivers" is shotty and current instructions don't
	always work. Read issue
        (<ulink url="https://github.com/Zeckmathederg/glfs/issues/6">
        #6</ulink>) on which issues are present.
      </para>

      <para>
        I don't have an estimate for how long I will be out. I
        just need time away from this project and not have to worry
        about LLVM, Rust, and Meson. I may accept pull requests.
      </para>

      <para>- Zeckma</para>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>~ Removal of Package Information</title>
      <para>June 4th, 2024</para>
      
      <para>
        In each page involving packages and their installation,
	there is a section called "Package Information," including
	various information such as the download link(s), download
	size, and estimated build time.
      </para>

      <para>
        Over the next few days, this section will be removed from
	every page. The download links will remain in each page.
        "Download size," "Download MD5 Sum," "Estimated disk space
	required," and "Estimated build time" will be removed.
      </para>

      <para>
        When packages are updated, all this information has to be
	checked, measured, and updated, demanding a lot of work to
	maintain everything. The removal of the "Package Information"
	section will make things much more manageable. Not to mention,
	I am terrible at maintaining projects as it is. SBUs are also
	good to know for each package but it can take a lot of time to
	measure and calculate the SBUs for each package. I cannot
	provide accurate SBU timing at this time. On a Ryzen 5 1600
	(has 6 cores and 12 threads), when typing and copy+pasting
	commands, going through the entire book took me 35 hours.
	If you have an application or script that can parse GLFS and
	run the commands automatically, the time will be comparable
	to Gentoo.
      </para>

      <para>
        Not the best of announcements, not the best of news. Sorry
	but this will help me maintain this book better.
      </para>
      <para>- Zeckma</para>
    </sect3>


    <sect3>
      <title>~ This is the first Bulletin Entry!</title>
      <para>June 1st, 2024</para>
      
      <para>
        This was made in anticipation for a few updates to come out, making
	changes that might be seen as weird or controversial. This offers as
	a section to explain those changes. <xref linkend="changelog"/> doesn't
        provide a good format to explain why commits and changes are being made,
	but rather just what changes were made.
      </para>
      <para>- Zeckma</para>
    </sect3>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
