<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="conventions">
  <?dbhtml filename="conventions.html"?>

  <sect1info>
    <othername>$LastChangedBy$</othername>
    <date>$Date$</date>
  </sect1info>

  <title>Conventions Used in this Book</title>

  <sect2>
  <title>Typographical Conventions</title>
  <para>To make things easy to follow, there are a number of conventions used
  throughout the book.  Following are some examples:</para>

<screen><userinput>./configure --prefix=/usr</userinput></screen>

  <blockquote>
    <para>This form of text is designed to be typed exactly as seen unless
    otherwise noted in the surrounding text. It is also used to identify
    references to specific commands.</para>
  </blockquote>

<screen><computeroutput>install-info: unknown option
`--dir-file=/mnt/lfs/usr/info/dir'</computeroutput></screen>

  <blockquote>
    <para>This form of text (fixed width text) is showing screen
    output, probably a result from issuing a command. It is also used to
    show filenames such as <filename>/boot/grub/grub.conf</filename></para>
  </blockquote>

  <para><emphasis>Emphasis</emphasis></para>

  <blockquote>
    <para>This form of text is used for several purposes in the
    book but mainly to emphasize important points or to give examples as to
    what to type.</para>
  </blockquote>

  <para><ulink url="http://www.&lfs-domainname;/"/></para>

  <blockquote>
    <para>This form of text is used for hypertext links external to
    the book such as HowTos, download locations, websites, etc.</para>
  </blockquote>

  <para><xref linkend="seamonkey"/></para>

  <blockquote>
    <para>This form of text is used for links internal to
    the book such as another section describing a different package.</para>
  </blockquote>

<screen><userinput>cat &gt; $LFS/etc/group &lt;&lt; "EOF"
<literal>root:x:0:
bin:x:1:
......</literal>
EOF</userinput></screen>

  <blockquote>
    <para>This type of section is used mainly when creating configuration
    files.  The first command (in bold) tells the system to create
    the file <filename>$LFS/etc/group</filename> from whatever is typed on the
    following lines until the sequence EOF is encountered.
    Therefore, this whole section is generally typed as seen.</para>
  </blockquote>

  <para><replaceable>&lt;REPLACED TEXT&gt;</replaceable></para>

  <blockquote>
    <para>This form of text is used to encapsulate text that should be
    modified and is not to be typed as seen, or copy and pasted. Note that
    the square brackets are not part of the text, but should be substituted
    for as well.</para>
  </blockquote>

  <para><systemitem class='username'>root</systemitem></para>

  <blockquote>
    <para>This form of text is used to show a specific system user or group
    reference in the instructions.</para>
  </blockquote>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>Conventions Used for Package Dependencies</title>

    <para>When packages are created, the authors depend on prior work.  In
    order to build a package in BLFS, these dependencies must be built prior to
    the desired package.  For each package, any prerequsite packages are listed
    in one or more separate sections:  Required, Recommended, and Optional.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect3">Required Dependencies</bridgehead>

    <para>These dependencies are the minimum prerequsite packages required to
    build the package.  Omitted from the list are packages in LFS and required
    dependencies of other required packages.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect3">Recommended Dependencies</bridgehead>

    <para>These dependencies are those that the BLFS editors have determined
    are important to give the package reasonable capabilities.  Package
    installation instructions assume they are installed.  If a recommended
    package is not desired, the instructions may need to be modified to
    accommodate the missing package.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect3">Optional Dependencies</bridgehead>

    <para>These dependencies are those that the package may use.  Integration
    of optional dependencies may be automatic by the package or may need
    additional instructions not presented by BLFS.  Optional packages may be
    listed without corresponding BLFS instructions.  In this case it is up to
    the user to determine appropriate installation instructions. </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>Conventions Used for Kernel Configuration Options</title>

    <para>Some packages have specific needs regarding the kernel configuration.
    The general layout is the following:</para>

<screen><literal>Master section ---&gt;
  Subsection ---&gt;
    [*]     Required parameter                     [CONFIG_REQU_PAR]
    &lt;*&gt;     Required parameter (not as module)     [CONFIG_REQU_PAR_NMOD]
    &lt;*/M&gt;   Required parameter (could be a module) [CONFIG_REQU_PAR_MOD]
    &lt;*/M/ &gt; Optional parameter                     [CONFIG_OPT_PAR]
    [ ] Incompatible parameter                     [CONFIG_INCOMP_PAR]
    &lt; &gt; Incompatible parameter (even as module)    [CONFIG_INCOMP_PAR_MOD]</literal></screen>

    <para>[CONFIG_...] on the right gives the name of the option, so you can
    easily check whether it is set in your <filename>config</filename> file.
    The meaning of the various entries is:

    <blockquote>
    <informaltable frame='none'><tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec align="left"/><colspec align="left"/><tbody>
      <row>
        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Master section</emphasis></entry>
        <entry>top level menu item</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Subsection</emphasis></entry>
        <entry>submenu item</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          <emphasis role="bold">Required parameter</emphasis></entry>
        <entry>
          the option could be either built-in or not selected: it must be
          selected
        </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          <emphasis role="bold">Required parameter (not as
          module)</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          the option could be either built-in, module, or not selected:
          it must be selected as built-in
        </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          <emphasis role="bold">Required parameter (could be
          a module)</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          the option could be either built-in, module, or not selected:
          it must be selected, either as built-in or module
        </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          <emphasis role="bold">Optional parameter</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          rarely used: the option could be either built-in, module, or not
          selected: it may be selected at will
        </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          <emphasis role="bold">Incompatible parameter</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          the option could be either built-in or not selected: it must
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> be selected
        </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>
          <emphasis role="bold">Incompatible parameter (even as module)</emphasis>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          the option could be either built-in, module, or not selected:
          it must <emphasis>not</emphasis> be selected
        </entry>
      </row>
    </tbody></tgroup></informaltable>
    </blockquote>
    </para>

    <para>Note that, depending on other selections, the angle brackets
    (&lt;&gt;) may appear as braces ({}), if the option cannot be unselected,
    or even dashes (-*- or -M-), when the choice is imposed.
    The help text about the option specifies the other selections on which this
    option relies, and how those other selections are set.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
  <title>SBU values in BLFS</title>

    <para>As in LFS, each package in BLFS has a build time listed in Standard
    Build Units (SBUs).   These times are relative to the time it took to build
    binutils in LFS and are intended to provide some insight into how long it
    will take to build a package. Most times listed are for a single processor
    or core to build the package. In some cases, large, long running builds
    tested on multi-core systems have SBU times listed with comments such
    as '(parallelism=4)'.  These values indicate testing was done using
    multiple cores.  Note that while this speeds up the build on systems with
    the appropriate hardware, the speedup is not linear and to some extent
    depends on the individual package and specific hardware used.  </para>

    <para>For packages which use ninja (e.g. anything using meson) or rust, by
    default all cores are used so similar comments will be seen on such packages
    even when the build time is minimal.</para>

    <para>Where even a parallel build takes more than 15 SBU, on certain
    machines the time may be considerably greater even when the build does not
    use swap. In particular, different micro-architectures will build some
    files at different relative speeds and this can introduce delays when
    certain make targets wait for another file to be created. Where a large
    build uses a lot of C++ files, processors with Simultaneous Multi Threading
    will share the Floating Point Unit and can take 45% longer than when using
    four 'prime' cores (measured on an intel i7 using taskset and keeping the
    other cores idle).</para>

    <para>Some packages do not support parallel builds and using -j1 for the
    make command is required.  Packages that are known to have such limits are
    marked as such in the text.</para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
