<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="rationale" xreflabel="Rationale for Packages">
  <?dbhtml filename="rationale.html"?>


  <title>Rationale for Packages</title>

  <para>
    Upon reading through some of the sections in this book, you may notice
    that a lot of the packages linked in some of the sections aren't in
    this book but rather in BLFS, and that some optional dependencies aren't
    even listed. Furthermore, some packages may be outdated. These choices
    are very much deliberate.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Why Are Many Packages Not in the Book?</title>

    <para>
	Many packages linked on some of the packages' sections aren't in
	the book but rather in the BLFS book. There are multiple reasons
	for this, but the most notable one is the packages that aren't in
	the book aren't important for the main packages in the book, those
	being <application>Steam</application> and <application>Wine
	</application>. They are still listed anyway if users want more
	support out of the specific packages not specific to the main
	packages, like media playback for example. Another reason for
	packages not being in the book is that the packages take a lot
	of work to install and require jumping around. They can also require
	a lot of choice or take up space or RAM for no real benefit for a
	lot of users when there are more simple solutions, for example: a
	logind variant being completely unnecessary as the regular user can
	just be added to the <systemitem class='groupname'>audio</systemitem>,
	<systemitem class='groupname'>video</systemitem>, and
	<systemitem class='groupname'>input</systemitem> groups.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Why Are Some Optional Dependencies Not Listed?</title>

    <para>
	There are some optional dependencies that aren't listed, and the
	main reason for this is that they just would take up unnecessary
	space. If on the offchance you desire even more out of your system,
	there are plenty more packages in BLFS and is more geared for
	everyone, although this book focuses more on gaming.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Packages That Are Outdated and Why</title>

    <para>
	GCC-&gcc-version; vs GCC-14.1.0: GCC-14.1.0 introduces a lot of
	bugs, leading to the inability to even compile the newest version
	with <application>MinGW-w64</application>. It also leads to
	unexpected test failures. Until these bugs are worked out, the
	<application>GCC</application> version will be &gcc-version;.
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
