<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="whichsections" xreflabel="Which sections of the book?">
  <?dbhtml filename="which.html"?>


  <title>Which Sections of the Book Do I Want?</title>

  <para>
    GLFS stands as a format in between LFS and BLFS so this
    part is crucial to understanding what you need to read and/or
    follow in order to get out of the system that you desire.
    For starters, LFS is meant to be followed in a linear manner,
    whereas BLFS handles things by putting related packages in
    the sections they are best described as categorically.
    For example, printer software being in a printer section,
    although most packages can be discarded by the user.
  </para>

  <para>
    As previously mentioned, GLFS stands as a format in
    between the two books. Not every chapter will be necessary
    but depending on what the user wants will have to read
    everything in the relevant chapter depending on if they
    desire to go with multilib or not, which is discussed in the
    multilib chapter.
  </para>

  <para>
    By default, every user should read the multilib chapter as
    most users that want Steam and/or Wine should have a x86_64
    CPU capable of 32-bit emulation. If that chapter is skipped,
    it might be realized to be a mistake and would cause a
    headache at the final stages.
  </para>

  <para>
    The following chapter is Shared Dependencies. Every user
    who wants Steam and/or Wine will want to read this chapter
    as both projects use the packages. Try as you may, but this
    chapter is absolutely necessary. However, it is recommended
    to check the dependency lists of Steam and Wine to see what
    exactly you need from that section instead of installing
    everything despite only needing maybe 90% of it.
  </para>

  <para>
    The next chapter is Steam, which covers all the packages,
    patches, configuration, and setup necessary to get Steam
    working and capable of the playing the following: Linux games,
    Windows games via Proton, games using OpenGL, games using
    Vulkan, games using D3D, and games using OpenXR. It covers
    both regular compilation of packages and lib32 compilation of
    some of the same packages. If you read the multilib section
    and decided that you desire NOT to go with multilib (despite
    any warnings), you can ignore the lib32 variants of packages).
    Otherwise, follow every step unless told otherwise in the
    respective sections or are presented with options.
  </para>

  <para>
    The last chapter that most users will need is Wine. Likewise
    with the Steam chapter, users should follow every step in this
    chapter if they want to install Wine and use it. The Wine
    chapter at the moment does not consider retrofitting and will
    handle it in a similar manner to Arch: get toolchains, install
    audio and video components, then finally Wine itself. This
    chapter will depend on packages listed in the Steam section, so
    when prompted, go to the package it lists which resides in the
    Steam section, then go back. This is done to avoid duplicate
    sections.
  </para>

  <para>
    We hope you enjoy using GLFS. May you realize that LFS can
    compete with just-works distros and even minimalist ones, instead
    of seeming like it's stuck in the past!
  </para>

</sect1>
