<partintro>
<title>Introduction to <acronym>KDE</acronym></title>

<para><acronym>KDE</acronym> is a comprehensive desktop environment that builds on 
<productname>XFree86</productname> and <productname>QT</productname> to provide
a window manager and many user tools, including a browser, word processor, 
spreadsheet, presentation package, games, and numerous other utilities. It 
provides extensive capabilities for customization.</para>

<para>We divide the <acronym>KDE</acronym> instructions into three parts. The first part, the
core packages, are needed for the rest of <acronym>KDE</acronym> to work. The second part
presents additional packages which provide functionality in various areas
(multimedia, graphics etc). Finally, we describe installation of other 
miscellaneous <acronym>KDE</acronym> packages.</para>

<para>As the instructions for compiling and installing <acronym>KDE</acronym> were developed,
the options to <filename>configure</filename> were examined and the parameters
presented are the most likely to compile correctly. In each of the packages,
one other option to <filename>configure</filename> can be added: 
<command>--enable-final</command>. This option can speed up the build 
process, but requires a lot of memory. If you have less than 256MB of RAM, 
this option may cause swapping and significantly slow compilation.</para>

<para><acronym>KDE</acronym> also has many internationalization packages in the form of:
<filename>kde-i18n-xx-&kde-version;.tar.bz2</filename>
where the xx is a two to five letter code for the country covered. We
do not cover the installation of these packages here.</para>

<para>All the <acronym>KDE</acronym> packages comprise of various components. The default is to
install most of the components. If specific components are to be eliminated, the
official way is to set the variable <userinput>DO_NOT_COMPILE</userinput>.
This comes in handy when there are problems compiling a particular
component.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>DO_NOT_COMPILE="component1 component2" \
./configure --prefix=/opt/kde...</command></userinput></screen>

<para>The core <acronym>KDE</acronym> packages also honor this variable, but omitting components
from the core packages is not advisable since it may result in an
incomplete <acronym>KDE</acronym> installation.</para>

</partintro>
