<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="bootscripts" xreflabel="blfs-bootscripts-&blfs-bootscripts-version;" revision="sysv">
  <?dbhtml filename="bootscripts.html"?>

  <sect1info>
    <othername>$LastChangedBy$</othername>
    <date>$Date$</date>
  </sect1info>

  <title>BLFS Boot Scripts</title>

  <indexterm zone="bootscripts">
    <primary sortas="a-BLFS-Bootscripts">BLFS Bootscripts</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm zone="bootscripts">
    <primary sortas="f-AA-General-Information">General Information</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>The BLFS Bootscripts package contains the init
  scripts that are used throughout the book. It is assumed that you will be
  using the BLFS Bootscripts package in conjunction with a compatible
  LFS-Bootscripts package. Refer to
  <ulink url="&lfs-root;/chapter07/bootscripts.html"/> for more
  information on the LFS-Bootscripts package.</para>

  <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
    <title>Package Information</title>
    <listitem>
      <para>Download: <ulink
        url="&sources-anduin-http;/blfs-bootscripts/blfs-bootscripts-&blfs-bootscripts-version;.tar.xz"/></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The BLFS Bootscripts package will be used throughout the BLFS book
  for startup scripts.  Unlike LFS, each init script has a separate install target
  in the BLFS Bootscripts package. It is recommended you keep the package source
  directory around until completion of your BLFS system. When a script is
  requested from BLFS Bootscripts, simply change to the directory and as the
  <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> user, execute the given
  <command>make install-<replaceable>&lt;init-script&gt;</replaceable></command>
  command. This command installs the init script to its proper location (along
  with any auxiliary configuration scripts) and also creates the appropriate
  symlinks to start and stop the service at the appropriate run-level.</para>

  <note>
    <para>You should review each bootscript before installation to
    ascertain that it satisfies your need. Also verify that the start and stop
    symlinks it creates match your preferences.</para>
  </note>

  <note>
    <para>From time to time the bootscripts are updated to accomodate
    new packages or to make minor corrections.  All versions of the
    bootscripts are located at <ulink
    url="&sources-anduin-http;/blfs-bootscripts/"/>.</para>
  </note>

</sect1>
