<sect1 id="intro-important-unpacking">
<?dbhtml filename="unpacking.html" dir="introduction"?>
<title>Getting and unpacking the software</title>

<para>Those people who have built a <acronym>LFS</acronym> system will be aware 
of the general principles of downloading and unpacking software.  We will
however repeat some of that information here for those new to building
their own software.</para>

<para>Each set of installation instructions contains a <acronym>URL</acronym> 
from which you can download the package.  We do however keep a selection of 
patches available via http.  These are referenced as needed in the
installation instructions.</para>

<para>While you can keep the source tarballs anywhere you like, we
assume that you have unpacked them and unzipped any required patches
into <filename>/usr/src</filename>.</para>

<para>We can not emphasize strongly enough that you should start from a
<emphasis>clean source tree</emphasis> each time.  This means that if
you have had an error, it's usually best to delete the source tree and
re-unpack it <emphasis>before</emphasis> trying again.  This obviously
doesn't apply if you're an advanced user used to hacking Makefiles and C
code, but if in doubt, start from a clean tree.</para>

<sect2>
<title>Unpacking the software</title>

<para>If a file is tar'ed and gzip'ed, it is unpacked by running one of
the following two commands, depending on the filename:</para>

<screen><command>tar -xvzf filename.tar.gz
tar -xvzf filename.tgz
tar -xvzf filename.tar.Z</command></screen>

<para>If a file is tar'ed and bzip2'ed, it can usually be unpacked by
running:</para>

<screen><command>tar -jxvf filename.tar.bz2</command></screen>

<para>You can also use a slightly different method:</para>

<screen><command>bzcat filename.tar.bz2 | tar -xv</command></screen>

<para>Finally, you need to be able to unpack patches which are generally
not tar'ed.  The best way to do this is to copy the patch file to
<filename>/usr/src</filename> and then to run one of the following
commands depending on whether the file is .gz or .bz2:</para>

<screen><command>gunzip patchname.gz
bunzip2 patchname.bz2</command></screen>

</sect2>

</sect1>
