<sect2>
<title>Installation of <application>OpenOffice</application></title>

<para>Apply the downloaded patches and optionally copy the gpc files.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>mv ../gpc231/* external/gpc &amp;&amp;
for p in ../openoffice-&openoffice-version;-*.patch
do patch -Np1 -i $p
done</command></userinput></screen>

<para>If you want to optimize the build, edit
<filename>solenv/inc/unxlngi4.mk</filename> and add the desired optimization
flags to the <envar>CFLAGSOPT</envar> variable. Some users have reported problems with
-fomit-frame-pointer. The best option is to not use any custom optimizations.
The following command removes an incorrect -mcpu option in the above file.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>sed -i "s:\-mcpu=pentiumpro::" \
solenv/inc/unxlngi4.mk</command></userinput></screen>

<para>Configure openoffice using the following commands. You may build install
sets for only specific languages based on your preferences.
If a particular component is not available
in the language of your choice, the default will be English.
The following option
compiles all available languages. If you restrict the languages, be sure to
add ENUS to the list; otherwise the build fails. Also, the build fails when
the environment variable <envar>LANG</envar> is
set. Unset it before compiling.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>cd config_office/ &amp;&amp;
./configure --with-lang=ALL \
--with-dict=ALL --without-fonts \
--enable-libsn --with-system-zlib &amp;&amp;
cd ..</command></userinput></screen>

<para>Compile <application>OpenOffice</application> using the following
commands.</para>

<note><para>Openoffice fails to compile if the umask is set to something exotic.
Set umask to 022 if you normally set it to something else.</para></note>

<screen><userinput><command>./bootstrap &amp;&amp;
bash -c "source LinuxIntelEnv.Set.sh; dmake"</command></userinput></screen>

<para>If you have downloaded localized help content zip files, you will need
to unzip them to the appropriate directory as mentioned below and then recreate
the installation set.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>cd solver/645/unxlngi4.pro/pck &amp;&amp;
for i in $(ls ../../../../../helpcontent_*_unix.tgz)
do
tar -xvzf $i
done &amp;&amp;
cd ../../../../instsetoo &amp;&amp;
rm -rf unxlngi4.pro &amp;&amp;
cd .. &amp;&amp;
bash -c "source LinuxIntelEnv.Set.sh ; dmake"</command></userinput></screen>

<para>Install <application>OpenOffice</application> using the following
commands to install the English language set. To install a localized version,
replace the 01 with the international telephone country code for your country.
Note that when installing, <application>OpenOffice</application> needs an
<application>X</application> display, even though there is no visible
<application>X</application> window. You can use
<application>Xvfb</application> if you are compiling on a console.</para>

<screen><userinput><command>cd instsetoo/unxlngi4.pro/01/normal &amp;&amp;
sed -i "s:^oo_home=.*:oo_home=openoffice:" install &amp;&amp;
./install --prefix=/opt &amp;&amp;
for appl in swriter scalc sdraw simpress smath soffice spadmin
do ln -sf /opt/openoffice/program/$appl /usr/bin/$appl
done</command></userinput></screen>

</sect2>

