<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<!--
$LastChangedBy$
$Date$
-->

<chapter id="pst-typesetting">
  <?dbhtml filename="typesetting.html"?>

  <title>Typesetting</title>

  <para>This chapter includes <application>texlive</application> applications that
  create output equivalent to typesetting.</para>

  <para>There are two alternative routes through this chapter:</para>

  <para>Some people may wish to use the binary installer, either because of the
  complexity of installing all of <application>texlive</application> from
  source, or because they only want a part of the package, or perhaps because
  they wish to get updates as soon as those are available (the source is only
  updated annually). These people should follow the <xref
  linkend="tl-installer"/> instructions,. After installing, they can run
  <command>tlmgr</command> to update their system.</para>

  <para>Most people reading BLFS will wish to build from source. You can either
  do as BLFS used to do, by starting with <application>install-tl-unx</application>,
  or you can avoid the binary files completely and begin at
  <xref linkend="texpass1"/> which will install most of
  <application>texlive</application>, together with <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the
  supporting files. This almost-complete install is then used to build two
  remaining parts of <application>texlive</application>, xindy and asy (that
  involves recompiling all of the package, but not reinstalling all of it).</para>

  <para>Because the texmf files (including documentation, fonts, scripts and
  supporting files) are all in one tarball, it is not practical to limit what
  gets extracted in a sensible way (e.g. to exclude one or other of the typesetting
  engines).</para>

  <para>After that, people building from source will wish to install <xref
  linkend="biber"/>, which is supplied separately, to complete the full
  installation.</para>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="tl-installer.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="texlive-pass1.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="tex-path.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="texlive.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="biber.xml"/>

</chapter>
