<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<!--
$LastChangedBy$
$Date$
-->

<chapter id="pst-typesetting">
  <?dbhtml filename="typesetting.html"?>

  <title>Typesetting</title>

  <para>This chapter includes <application>texlive</application> applications that
  create output equivalent to typesetting.</para>

  <para>There are two alternative routes through this chapter:</para>

  <para>Some people may wish to use the binary installer, either because of the
  complexity of installing all of <application>texlive</application> from
  source, or because they only want a part of the package, or perhaps because
  they wish to get updates as soon as those are available (the source is only
  updated annually). These people should follow the <xref
  linkend="tl-installer"/> instructions,. After installing, they can run
  <command>tlmgr</command> to update their system.</para>

  <para>Most people reading BLFS will wish to build from source. BLFS used to
  start by installing <application>install-tl-unx</application> and then use that
  to bootstrap the build.  Nowadays, we build almost the whole of
  <application>texlive</application> <emphasis>without</emphasis> a binary install,
  by adding the separately-packaged texmf files into this build.  For this, begin
  at <xref linkend="texlive"/> which will install most of
  <application>texlive</application>, together with <emphasis>all</emphasis> of the
  supporting files. This almost-complete install can then be used to build the
  remaining parts of <application>texlive</application>, <xref
  linkend="asymptote"/>, <xref linkend="xindy"/> and <xref linkend="biber"/>.
  </para>

  <para>Because the texmf files (including documentation, fonts, scripts and
  supporting files) are all in one tarball, it is not practical to limit what
  gets extracted in a sensible way (e.g. to exclude one or other of the typesetting
  engines) when building from source in this manner.</para>

  <para>In either case, BLFS installs into
  <filename class="directory">/opt/texlive/&texlive-year;</filename> with the sole
  exception of two libraries from the source install which are installed into
  <filename class="directory">/usr/lib</filename> for convenience.</para>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="tl-installer.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="texlive.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="tex-path.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="biber.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="xindy.xml"/>

</chapter>
