<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="needml" xreflabel="Do I Need Multilib?">
  <?dbhtml filename="needml.html"?>


  <title>Do I Need Multilib?</title>

  <para>
    If you have a CPU that is capable of multilib, it is time
    to decide whether to go for it or not. Depending on the
    circumstance, it may be necessary to go for it.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Steam</title>
    
    <para>
	Most gamers would not know this unless they push the
	limits of the game they play, but many games on Steam
	are 32-bit. Some games are no longer receiving updates
	while some are still being updated but are still 32-bit
	to this day. A good example of this is Geometry Dash,
	the developer of GD, RobTop, made plans to switch to
	64-bit, but that hasn't come to fruition yet, and thus
	leads to many issues such as online levels having too
	many objects that require a big amount of RAM but the
	32-bit application can't use that much RAM, which
	results in a crash.
    </para>

    <para>
	Not only are a lot of games 32-bit, but Steam itself
	requires that you have 32-bit libraries. If the 32-bit
	libraries aren't on the system, Steam will quit, saying
	it needs a library, libc.so.6 being the most common
	example. So if you have a 64-bit CPU, you will need the
	ability to execute 32-bit applications as well as all the
	libraries necessary which is laid out in Chapter 3.
    </para>

    <para>
	If you have a 32-bit CPU, you can skip the 32-bit libraries
	and compile everything normally as they will build for your
	architecture.
    </para>

    <important>
	<para>
	  Steam will eventually kill off 32-bit CPU support so be wary
	  that while you can run Steam with a 32-bit CPU, in the future
	  perhaps sometime soon, you will no longer be able to do this.
	</para>
    </important>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Wine</title>
      
    <para>
	Unlike Steam, Wine does not require that you have 32-bit libraries
	or the i686-w64-mingw32 toolchain. Moreover, to get multilib
	support in Wine, it must be compiled twice: a w64 build and a w32
	w/ w64 build. However, it was discussed eariler in the Steam
	section that many games are 32-bit and are no longer maintained or
	will take a while to switch to 64-bit. This is the case with
	Windows applications as well. This means that if you do a 64-bit
	only build, compatabilty for all those 32-bit applications will
	be lost.
    </para>

    <para>
	A Wine WoW64 (can run 32-bit and 64-bit applications) build is
	recommended. If you do not have a 64-bit CPU, then follow only
	the i686 build instructions. Likewise, if you have a 64-bit
	CPU, then you can follow only the x86_64 build instructions.
	The mingw-w64 toolchain is also really helpful for developers,
	so if you don't want full support with Wine but full support
	for the mingw-w64 toolchain, then by all means: go for it.
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
