<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE bookinfo PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<bookinfo>
<title>Beyond <trademark class='registered'>Linux</trademark> From Scratch</title>
<subtitle>Version &version;</subtitle>


<authorgroup>
<corpauthor>
        BLFS Development Team
</corpauthor>
</authorgroup>

<pubdate>&pubdate;</pubdate>


<copyright id="copyright">
	<year>2001-2004</year>
    <holder>BLFS Development Team</holder>
</copyright>


<legalnotice>

<para>Copyright &copy; 2001-2004, <acronym>BLFS</acronym> Development Team</para>

<para>All rights reserved.</para>

<para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
met:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Redistributions in any form must retain the above copyright 
notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Neither the name of "Linux From Scratch" nor the names of 
its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from 
this material without specific prior written permission.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Any material derived from Linux From Scratch must contain 
a reference to the "Linux From Scratch" project.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS
IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE REGENTS OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
(INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES;
LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON
ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
(INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>

<para><trademark class='registered'>Linux</trademark> is a registered trademark of 
Linus Torvalds.</para>


</legalnotice>

<revhistory>
<revision>
	<revnumber>&version;</revnumber>
	<date>&pubdate;</date>
	<revremark>Development release</revremark>
</revision>

<revision>
	<revnumber>5.1</revnumber>
	<date>2004-6-05</date>
	<revremark>Third release</revremark>
</revision>

<revision>
	<revnumber>5.0</revnumber>
	<date>2003-11-06</date>
	<revremark>Second release</revremark>
</revision>

<revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>2003-04-25</date>
	<revremark>First release</revremark>
</revision>
</revhistory>


<abstract role="dsssl">

<para>This book follows on from the Linux From Scratch book.  It introduces and
guides the reader through additions to the system including networking, X
support, sound support and printer and scanner support.</para>

</abstract>

</bookinfo>
