<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<preface id="preface" xreflabel="Preface">
  <?dbhtml filename="preface.html" dir="preface"?>

  <title>Preface</title>

  <para>
	After around 2 or 3 months of my first ever install of Linux From Scratch,
	I had an question: how do I install <application>Steam</application> on
	this? After some time, I went for Beyond Linux From Scratch, a very great
	book that covered most of what I both wanted and needed, but my
	<application>Steam</application> question never got answered. So I just
	tried to install the <application>Steam</application> tarball and I went
	down the rabbit hole.
  </para>

  <para>
	Beyond Linux From Scratch didn't show how so I felt alone and on my own.
	I learned shortly after my attempt that I need multilib, and Bruce Dubbs
	saw my email and responded quite promptly saying to go to Thomas' Multilib
	mirror. This made all the difference, but now I needed to find out all the
	packages to install, all the configuration.
  </para>

  <para>
	Rahul Chandra in the same thread mentioned his scripts for his distro,
	Tucana. These scripts helped so much, even if all the scripts were
	presented all at once. Once I had got <application>Steam</application>
	to work, I realized that in some way, somehow, I must share how I did it
	and to help others with a single comprehensive guide.
  </para>

  <para>
	At some point, I also decided to try to get Wine to work. I was successful.
	I, again like with <application>Steam</application> before, wanted to share
	the process. Rahul reached out to me, and that led to this book's creation
	and editing.
  </para>

  <para>
	Thank you, and I hope this helps you.
  </para>

  <blockquote>
<literallayout>Zeckma
zeckmaisreal &lt;at&gt; gmail.com</literallayout>
  </blockquote>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="foreword.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="whoread.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="organization.xml"/>
  <!-- <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="errata.xml"/> -->

</preface>
