<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="gpuconfig" xreflabel="GPU Kernel Options and Firmware">
  <?dbhtml filename="gpuconfig.html"?>


  <title>GPU Kernel Options and Firmware</title>

  <para>
    The Linux kernel has multiple drivers for all sorts of hardware,
    including GPUs, and most open source drivers are in the kernel.
    This includes AMD, i915, and Nouveau. There are other drivers
    as well that can be useful for certain users. Firmware is also
    necessary for many drivers.
  </para>

  <sect2 role="kernel" id="gpu-kernel" xreflabel='GPU Kernel Configuration'>
    <title>Kernel Configuration</title>

    <para>
	The kernel options below enable GPU and virtual GPU drivers.
	Enable the ones you need and recompile the kernel if necessary.
    </para>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="gpuconfig-kernel.xml"/>

    <note>
    <para>
	There are comments for the options above, corresponding with Mesa's
	Gallium3D dri driver names.
    </para>

    <para>
	Selecting <option>CONFIG_DRM_RADEON</option>,
	<option>CONFIG_DRM_AMDGPU</option>, or
	<option>CONFIG_DRM_NOUVEAU</option> as
	<quote><literal>y</literal></quote> is not recommended. If it is, any
	required firmware must be built as a part of the kernel image or the
	initramfs for the driver to function correctly.
    </para>

    <para>
	The sub-entries under <option>CONFIG_DRM_AMDGPU</option> are used
	to ensure the AMDGPU kernel driver supports all GPUs using the
	<literal>radeonsi</literal> driver.  They are not needed if you
	won't need <option>CONFIG_DRM_AMDGPU</option> itself. They
	may be unneeded for some GPU models.
    </para>

    <para>
	For <literal>swrast</literal>, <option>CONFIG_DRM_VGEM</option>
	is not strictly needed but recommended as an optimization.
    </para>
    </note>

    <indexterm zone="gpuconfig gpu-kernel">
      <primary sortas="d-gpuconfig">gpuconfig</primary>
    </indexterm>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Firmware</title>

    <sect3>
      <title>ATI Firmware</title>

      <para>
	ATI Radeon GPUs require firmware to be able to use KMS (kernel
	modesetting - the preferred option) as well as for Xorg. For
	older Radeon chips before r600, the firmware is in the kernel
	source. Later GPUs have their firmware in <application>
	linux-firmware</application>.
      </para>

      <para>
	In order to save space, it is recommended to use
	<xref linkend="pciutils"/> and it's packaged binary <command>
	lspci</command> to identify what the VGA controller is. After
	you find out that, check the RadeonFeature page of the Xorg
	wiki for 
	<ulink url="https://wiki.x.org/wiki/RadeonFeature/#index5h2">
	Decoder ring for engineering vs marketing names</ulink> to
	identify the family (you may need to know this for the Xorg
	driver — Southern Islands and Sea Islands use the radeonsi
	driver) and the specific model.
      </para>

      <para>
	Now that you know which controller you are using, consult the
	<ulink url="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Radeon#Firmware">
	Radeon Firmware</ulink> page of the Gentoo wiki which has a
	table listing the required firmware blobs for the various
	chipsets. Note that Southern Islands and Sea Islands chips
	use different firmware for kernel 3.17 and later compared to
	earlier kernels. Identify and download the required blobs
	then install them:
      </para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -pv /lib/firmware/radeon
cp -v &lt;YOUR_BLOBS&gt; /lib/firmware/radeon</userinput></screen>

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>RadeonSI Firmware</title>

      <para>
	AMDGPU devices require firmware in order to be used in general.
        Install <xref linkend="pciutils"/> to check the model name of
	your card, and look for 'VGA compatible controller:'. If you have
	an APU (Accelerated Processing Unit, i.e. CPU and video on the same
	chip) that will probably tell you the name. If you have a separate
	amdgpu video card you will need to search to determine which name it
	uses (e.g. a card described as Advanced Micro Devices, Inc. [AMD/ATI]
	Baffin [Radeon RX 550 640SP / RX 560/560X] need Polaris11 firmware.
	There is a table of "Family, Chipset name, Product name and Firmware"
	at the end of the Kernel sections in <ulink
	url="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/AMDGPU#Known_firmware_blobs">AMDGPU
        </ulink> page of the Gentoo wiki.
      </para>

      <para>
        Once you have identified the firmware name, install all the relevant
	files for it. For example, the Baffin card mentioned above has 21
	different polaris11* files, APUs such as renoir and picasso have at
	least 12 files and might gain more in future updates (e.g. the raven
	APU now has a 13th file, raven_ta.bin).
      </para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -pv /lib/firmware/amdgpu
cp -v &lt;YOUR_BLOBS&gt; /lib/firmware/amdgpu</userinput></screen>

      <para>
        If disk space is not a problem, you could install all the current
	amdgpu firmware files and not worry about exactly which chipset is
	installed.
      </para>

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>i915 Firmware</title>

      <para>
	Intel integrated GPUs from Skylake onwards can use firmware for
	GuC (the Graphics microcontroller), and also for the HuC
	(HEVC/H265 microcontroller which offloads to the GPU) and the
	DMC (Display Microcontroller) to provide additional low-power
	states. The GuC and HuC have had a chequered history in the
	kernel and updated firmware may be disabled by default,
	depending on your kernel version.Further details may be found at
	<ulink url="https://01.org/linuxgraphics/downloads/firmware/"/> and
	<ulink url="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/intel_graphics"/>.
      </para>

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Nouveau Firmware</title>

      <para>
	Nvidia GPUs from Kepler onwards require signed firmware, otherwise
	the nouveau driver is unable to provide hardware acceleration.
	Nvidia has now released firmware up to Ampere (GeForce30 series) to
	<application>linux-firmware</application>. Note that faster clocks
	than the default are not enabled by the released firmware.
      </para>

      <para>
        For older chips, it might be necessary to extract firmware from the
	NVIDIA runfile directly:
      </para>

<screen><userinput>wget https://anduin.linuxfromscratch.org/BLFS/nvidia-firmware/extract_firmware.py
wget https://us.download.nvidia.com/XFree86/Linux-x86/340.32/NVIDIA-Linux-x86-340.32.run
sh NVIDIA-Linux-x86-340.32.run --extract-only
python3 extract_firmware.py
mkdir -p /lib/firmware/nouveau
cp -d nv* vuc-* /lib/firmware/nouveau/</userinput></screen>

      <para>
        For newer chips, the nouveau driver searches in multiple paths,
	and simply grabbing firmware you find in the linux-firmware repository
	won't do any good probably. There are plenty of symlinks that need to
	be made. Follow the instructions below in order to install the newer
	firmware properly:
      </para>

<screen><userinput>git clone https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/firmware/linux-firmware.git/
cd linux-firmware
mkdir -pv /lib/firmware/nvidia
mkdir -pv DESTDIR/lib/firmware
sh copy-firmware.sh --ignore-duplicates DESTDIR/lib/firmware
cp -vr DESTDIR/lib/firmware/nvidia/* /lib/firmware/nvidia
rm -rf DESTDIR</userinput></screen>

    </sect3>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
