<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="whatdriver" xreflabel="What Drivers to Install">
  <?dbhtml filename="whatdriver.html"?>


  <title>What Drivers to Install</title>

  <para>
    On Linux, there are multiple drivers that one can install. Choosing
    the one you need can be difficult if you do not know what drivers
    are for what vendor and the perks and downsides of each option.
    This section explains all of that to better help you decide what
    you want or need.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title>AMD</title>

    <para>
	There are 3 AMD GPU drivers: AMDGPU (Radeon Southern Islands and later),
	ATI (r300 and r600), and AMDGPU PRO (proprietary AMDGPU driver).
    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>AMDGPU</emphasis>:
	this driver is for AMD GPUs that are Southern Island Cards or
	later. It is open source and is the most standard AMD GPU driver.
	This driver is in the Linux kernel and has two Mesa dri drivers:
	Gallium driver - <emphasis>radeonsi</emphasis> and Vulkan driver -
	<emphasis>amd</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>ATI</emphasis>:
	this driver is for the ATI AMD GPUs which precede GCN GPUs.
	It is open source and targets older GPUs. The driver is in the Linux
	kernel and has three Mesa dri drivers: Gallium drivers - <emphasis>
	r300</emphasis> and <emphasis>r600</emphasis>; and Vulkan driver -
	<emphasis>amd</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>AMDGPU PRO</emphasis>:
	this driver is proprietary. Most users don't need this
	driver as performance with the open source drivers are well off
	already. Those that need this driver may care about enterprise/LTS
	or using workstation applications that demand a lot of performance.
	Performance with the open source driver, however, often exceed
	this driver's performance, especially when playing games. Therefore,
	this driver isn't included in this book but there is a useful Arch
	Linux wiki page regarding more about <emphasis>AMDGPU PRO</emphasis>
	and its installation at
	<ulink url="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/AMDGPU_PRO"/>.
    </para>

    <para>
	Summary: If you are a regular user with a modern AMD GPU, use
	<emphasis>AMDGPU</emphasis>. If you have an older card, go with
	<emphasis>ATI</emphasis>. Use <emphasis>AMDGPU PRO</emphasis> if
	you want a possible improvement with workstation applications,
	but avoid it if you are aiming to play games are high performance.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Intel</title>

    <para>
	Intel provides open source drivers, but for sake of simplicity, all
	the relevant open source drivers will be classified as one -
	<emphasis>i915</emphasis>. There is another driver called <emphasis>
	uvesafb</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>i915</emphasis>: this driver, or rather collection of drivers,
	is for most Intel integrated and discrete GPUs. It is a single option
	in the Linux kernel but has various Mesa Gallium3D and Vulkan dri drivers.
	There is a good list on the MESA page under Command Explanations that
	will explain what Gallium3D and Vulkan driver you will need.
    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>uvesafb</emphasis>: this driver is for the Intel GMA 3600
	series, a family of integrated video adapters based on the PowerVR
	SGX 545 graphics core. This driver was in the kernel since 3.5 but
	no longer since 4.15. This driver is not included in the book
	because of its lack of use by most people, but has a good Arch Linux
	wiki page at <ulink url="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Intel_GMA_3600"/>.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>NVIDIA</title>

    <para>
	The situation revolving around NVIDIA is more unfortunate than
	the two vendors listed above and more complicated. NVIDIA does not
	support open source drivers besides their own open source kernel
	modules. Therefore performance with the open source drivers,
	<emphasis>Nouveau</emphasis> and <emphasis>NVK</emphasis>, are
	worse than NVIDIA's proprietary driver, although installing the
	proprietary driver is easier and doesn't require installing
	lib32-<application>mesa</application> for multilib.
    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>Nouveau</emphasis>: this driver is open source and
	has worse performance than <emphasis>NVIDIA</emphasis>. It is
	technically all a kernel driver, a Mesa Gallium3D driver, and
	Mesa Vulkan driver, although they have different parts and the
	Vulkan driver is often referred to as <emphasis>NVK</emphasis>,
	depsite being referred to as nouveau in Mesa's <parameter>
	-Dvulkan-drivers=</parameter> option.
    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>NVK</emphasis>: this driver is a new Mesa dri driver
	and in its production, involved several kernel patches. It is
	a Vulkan driver targetting Turing and later NVIDIA GPUs. It does
	provide better performance than <emphasis>Nouveau</emphasis> and
	is still improving. If you want to compile this driver, you are
	going to need Rust, and if you are doing multilib, are going
	to need the i686-unknown-linux-gnu target. Also make sure to install
	<emphasis>Nouveau</emphasis> if you want to install this driver.
    </para>

    <para>
	<emphasis>NVIDIA</emphasis>: This is the proprietary driver and
	the most often recommended for NVIDIA GPU owners using Linux.
	The performance of this driver exceeds the open source alternatives
	and allows the use of NVIDIA's CUDA project, useful for hardware
	acceleration, improving performance of games and workstation
	applications. This driver has a lot of issues to this day but
	still provides better performance, thus its installation is
	provided in this book. Installing this driver also prevents the
	need to install lib32-Mesa and lib32-LLVM if you are doing multilib.
	Firmware also isn't needed as it is provided by this driver.
    </para>

    <para>
	Summary: if you want good performance and care about workstation
	use cases, install <emphasis>NVIDIA</emphasis>. If you only use
	OpenGL applications and don't want the proprietary NVIDIA driver,
	use <emphasis>Nouveau</emphasis>. If you use a variety of
	applications and play games that utilize DirectX and Vulkan, install
	both <emphasis>Nouveau</emphasis> and <emphasis>NVK</emphasis>.
    </para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
